A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Education, Sexuality, and Religion unit, Office Files of Cyrus Driver FA1844
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Education, Sexuality, and Religion unit, Office Files of Cyrus Driver
1960-2010
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Driver, Cyrus
FA1844
6.81 Cubic Feet 19 document boxes: 17 letter size boxes, 1 oversize box, and 1 AV half-letter box
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2021 in two different sets of records and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2021:079 and Accession 2021:116.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the files Cyrus Driver created during his support and leadership of the Ford Foundation's programming for education from the late 1990s to the 2000s. The majority of the collection's content originates from between 1998 and 2005. During that time, Driver served as a Program Officer in the Foundation's Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC), Education, Knowledge, and Religion unit (EKR), then as a Program Officer in the Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Education, Sexuality, and Religion unit (ESR), and then as Deputy Director of the KCF ESR unit. Little documentation on Driver's later career at the Foundation as Director of Program Learning and Innovation is included within the collection.
The collection is comprised of one series of subject files. These files primarily document Driver's grant portfolio responsibilities for the Foundation's areas of focus in education as well as his engagement with the larger philanthropic field's interest in education. Driver managed grants that specifically focused on public school reform, particularly for schools in urban districts, improving access for teacher professional development, assessment of school systems, community involvement in school systems, and making education more equitable. Support for undergraduate preparation, community colleges, and preventing anti-LGBTQ discrimination and harassment in schools is also documented. A large number of files pertain to the Ford Foundation's Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI).
Common material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, notes, reports, drafts, grant recommendations, publications, news articles, and meeting materials. There is also a VHS tape and a few digital media items.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1960-2010
Ford Foundation; Community colleges; Community and school; Educational change; Educational equalization; Educational evaluation; Public schools; Teachers -- Training of -- United States; Urban schools
- Subject files, 1960-2010; 1; 6.81 Cubic Feet 19 document boxes: 17 letter size boxes, 1 oversize box, and 1 AV half-letter box
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files Cyrus Driver created and maintained when he worked in the Ford Foundation's Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC), Education, Knowledge, and Religion unit (EKR) and Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Education, Sexuality, and Religion unit (ESR). Driver worked as a Program Officer in EMAC EKR and then KCF ESR and then was Deputy Director for KCF ESR.
  Files in the series pertaining to Driver's grant portfolio responsibilities largely concern the Foundation's support of organizations seeking to improve public schools. Many records show Driver's work on the Foundation's Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) which sought to increase public support for education reform in communities. CERI funded eight different sites to promote increased professional development for teachers and increased parental and community involvement in schools. Driver's CERI files document site proposal responses, site visits, and site assessments from the RAND Corporation.
  Other grantee related files concern support for making education more equitable, for preparing undergraduate students for college, community colleges through the Rural Community College Initiative (RCCI) and Community Colleges Bridges to Opportunity (CCBOI), and for preventing anti-LGBTQ discrimination and harassment in schools. Correspondence, notes, grant recommendations, reports, promotional materials, and meeting materials make up these files. The Ford Foundation's engagement with other foundations and philanthropic organizations' involvement with education is also documented within the series.
  Other common material formats found in the collection that have not been previously mentioned include news articles, publications, a VHS tape, and a few digital media items. A few of the publications are located at the end of the series.
  - Institute on Education and Economy (IEE), 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interfaith Education Fund (IEF), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jobs for the Future, Hilary Pennington, 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Justice Matters Institute (JMI), 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rural Community College Initiative (RCCI)/MDRC, evaluators - Education Work, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rural Community College Initiative (RCCI)/MDRC, evaluators, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rural Community College Initiative (RCCI)/MDRC, evaluators, 1989-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rural Community College Initiative (RCCI)/MDRC, evaluators, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - National Black Child Development Institute (NBCDI), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Board of Education Testing and Public Policy (NBETPP), 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Project GRAD Newark, New Jersey (Adrian Gonzales), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Project GRAD Newark, New Jersey (Adrian Gonzales) - Convenings, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Project GRAD Newark, New Jersey (Adrian Gonzales), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Project GRAD Newark, New Jersey (Adrian Gonzales), 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Yale University Child Study Center (James Colmer and Valerie Maholmes), 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Young Audiences, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - SERVE at the University of North Carolina at Greensboro, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Funders - Community Foundation of Tampa Bay, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Funders - Grantmakers for Education, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Funders - Knight Foundation, 1996 November (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Funders - Open Society Institute (OSI), 1998 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Funders - Posner-Wallace Foundation, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Funders - Ashoka, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Funders - Association of Black Foundation Executives (ABFE), 1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Funders - Schools Around the World (SAW), 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Funders - Annie E. Casey Foundation (AECF), 1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Funders - Association of Black Foundation Executives (ABFE), 2005 April 4 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - The Urban Institute - Florida Voucher Program, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Donors' Education Collaborative (DEC), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Donors' Education Collaborative (DEC), 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Donors' Education Collaborative (DEC), 1998 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ford Foundation miscellaneous - Institute for International Education (IIE) Global Travel and Learning Fund (GTLF), 1999 October 19 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Ford Foundation miscellaneous - ffNet (Ford Foundation intranet), 1999 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - People of America Foundation - Allan Kullen and Leslie Thornton (Patton Boggs LLP), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - University of Maryland, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Grantmakers for Education (GFE), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Getty/Arts Education Coalition, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - William Caspar Graustein Memorial Fund - Bridgeport Child Advocacy Coalition (BCAC), 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - William Caspar Graustein Memorial Fund - David Nee visit, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - William Caspar Graustein Memorial Fund - Cyrus Driver visit to Fund, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Management Leadership Meetings (Performance Appraisals) - Self-appraisals, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Management Leadership Meetings (Performance Appraisals), 2001-2005 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Management Leadership Meetings (Performance Appraisals) - Policies and administration, 1990-2001 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Program related materials - Education Learning Circles, Guadalajara, Mexico, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Program related materials - Education, Sexuality, and Religion unit (ESR), 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Program related materials - Environmental education, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Program related materials - Smith Family Foundation, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Designs for Change, 1983-2002 (Box 4, Folder 48-50)
  - DoubleTake, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 51-52)
  - Education Through Music (ETM) Annual Report, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Education/Assessment - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Education/Assessment - Harvard University Civil Rights Project, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Educational Video Center (EVC), 2000-2002 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Fordham University National Center for Schools and Communities, John Beam, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - From the Top, Francis Hunnewell, 2000-2001 (Box 18, Folder 58)
  - From The Top Program 042, 2000 March 17 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - From The Top - A showcase of America's finest young classical musicians with Christopher O'Riley, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Fund for Community Organizing, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Fund for Community Organizing - Constituency building, 1996-1999 (Box 5, Folder 60-61)
  - Fund for Community Organizing - Constituency building meeting, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Fund for Community Organizing, 1994-2000 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Gay, Lesbian and Straight Education Network (GLSEN), 1998-2001 (Box 5, Folder 64-65)
  - GEAR UP (Gaining early Awareness and Readiness for Undergraduate Programs), 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - GEAR UP (Gaining Early Awareness and Readiness for Undergraduate Programs), 1999 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Institute for Gay and Lesbian Strategic Studies (IGLSS), 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Institute for Wisconsin's Future (IWF), 1998-2001 (Box 6, Folder 69-70)
  - Schools First Project, 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Annual New York Programming Review Meeting, Tarrytown, New York, 1995-1998 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Education Learning Circle Meeting, St. Petersburg, Russia, 1999-2002 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - School Communities that Work (SCtW) Meeting, Santa Fe, New Mexico, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Ford Foundation Joint Worldwide Meeting - Faces of the Ford Foundation Family, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) Retreat, Glen Cove, New York, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Project consultant proposals, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) Retreat, Glen Cove, New York, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Report on the Ford Foundation Fund for Community Organizing Phase 1 - Part 2, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Organizing and Constituency Building for Education Reform - A Briefing on Recent Research, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Ford Foundation Arts Education Initiative Grantee Convening, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Project GRAD Newark, New Jersey Fall 1999 Retreat, 2000 July 12 (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Project GRAD Newark Fall 1999 Retreat, circa 1999-2000; VHS; 16 minutes (Box 1, Tape AV 13105)
      Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Ford Foundation Joint Worldwide Meeting, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - National Training Institute - Organizing for Educational Excellence, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) evaluators - RAND Corporation, 1998-2002 (Box 8, Folder 85-86)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) evaluators - RAND Corporation, 1999-2000 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) evaluators - RAND Corporation, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) evaluators - RAND Corporation, 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 89-90)
  - Community organizing for schools, 1995-2001 (Box 9, Folder 91-94)
  - Standards, testing, and accountability, part 1, 1999-2002 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Standards, testing, and accountability, part 2, 1996-2002 (Box 10, Folder 96-98)
  - Collaboration reports, part 1, 1996-2000 (Box 10, Folder 99-100)
  - Collaboration reports, part 2, 1999-2002 (Box 11, Folder 101-102)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Convening at Ford Foundation, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 103)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Convening at Ford Foundation, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 104)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Chicago ACORN, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 105)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), project consultant, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 106)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), project consultant - Convening, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 107)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), project consultant - Miami, Florida, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), project consultant - Convening at Ford Foundation, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), project consultant, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), project consultant, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), project consultant, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 112)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Request for proposals, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 113)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Request for proposals planning, 1997-1999 (Box 12, Folder 114-115)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), 1997 (Box 12, Folder 116)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI), 1998 (Box 12, Folder 117)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Planning materials, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - Collaboration work and explorations - Arts and education, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Education, Knowledge, and Religion unit (EKR) - Cyrus Driver Program Officer Memo, undated (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Cyrus Driver Program Officer Memo, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Personal benefits, 1998-1999 (Box 17, Folder 174)
    Restricted Health information Open in 2100
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Charlotte-Mecklenburg, North Carolina, 1998-2002 (Box 12, Folder 122-123)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Charlotte-Mecklenburg, North Carolina implementation site, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 124)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Charlotte-Mecklenburg, North Carolina, 1999-2002 (Box 13, Folder 125-127)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Charlotte-Mecklenburg, North Carolina, 1996-1999 (Box 13, Folder 128)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Miami, Florida, 1998-1999 (Box 13, Folder 129)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Miami, Florida, 1998-1999 (Box 14, Folder 130)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Miami, Florida implementation site, 1999-2000 (Box 14, Folder 131)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Denver, Colorado site visit, 1995-2001 (Box 14, Folder 132)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Denver, Colorado, 1998-2001 (Box 14, Folder 133)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Denver, Colorado implementation site, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 134)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Denver, Colorado, 1994-1999 (Box 14, Folder 135)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Denver, Colorado, 1997-1999 (Box 14, Folder 136)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Denver, Colorado, 1997-1999 (Box 14, Folder 137)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Jackson, Mississippi, 2003-2004 (Box 14, Folder 138)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Jackson, Mississippi site visit, 2001-2002 (Box 14, Folder 139)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Jackson, Mississippi, 1995-2002 (Box 15, Folder 140)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Jackson, Mississippi implementation site, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 141)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Jackson, Mississippi site visit, 1999-2001 (Box 15, Folder 142)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Jackson, Mississippi, 1995-1999 (Box 15, Folder 143)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Jackson, Mississippi, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 144)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Jackson, Mississippi, 1999-2004 (Box 15, Folder 145-147)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Chicago, Illinois, 2002-2004 (Box 15, Folder 148)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Washington D.C., 2004-2005 (Box 15, Folder 149)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Various reports, 2000-2004 (Box 15, Folder 150)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - RAND Corporation, 2004 (Box 16, Folder 151)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 2004 (Box 16, Folder 152)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Santa Ana, California site implementation, 1998-2000 (Box 16, Folder 153)
  - Collaborating for Educational Reform Initiative (CERI) - Grantees, Santa Ana, California, 1999-2001 (Box 16, Folder 154)
  - Learning Circle working file, 1995-2001 (Box 16, Folder 155)
  - Learning Circle working file - San Juan, Puerto Rico meeting, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 156)
  - Learning Circle working file - San Juan, Puerto Rico meeting, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 157)
  - Grants portfolio and general overall work, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 158)
  - Stanford University email programs - Pine and Elm, 1996-1998 (Box 16, Folder 159)
  - Community Colleges Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Denver, Colorado, 1988-2002 (Box 16, Folder 160)
  - Community Colleges Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Ohio, 2001-2002 (Box 16, Folder 161)
  - Community Colleges Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Kentucky, 1998-2002 (Box 16, Folder 162)
  - Community Colleges Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Colorado, circa 1988-2002 (Box 16, Folder 163)
  - Community Colleges Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Washington, 2002 (Box 16, Folder 164)
  - Community Colleges Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Iowa, 1999-2002 (Box 16, Folder 165)
  - Community Colleges Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Mississippi, 1960-2002 (Box 17, Folder 166)
  - Crossing Borders: Revitalizing Area Studies, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 167)
  - Power, Participation, and State-Based Politics: An Evaluation of the Ford Foundation' Collaborations that Count Initiative, 2004 (Box 17, Folder 168-169)
  - Ford Foundation Initiative Summaries Fall 2009 (Box 17, Folder 170)
  - Ford Foundation Regional Summaries Fall 2009 (Box 17, Folder 171)
  - Ford Foundation 2010 Program Staff Orientation Handbook (Box 17, Folder 172)
  - Arts Education for All: Lessons from the First Half of the Ford Foundation's National Arts Education Initiative, circa 2008 (Box 17, Folder 173)